<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle dedicated to an honourable person in the which are discouered a dozen bad spirits, who from the beginning haue much haunted &amp; grieuously tormented the Protestant congregation, so that euery one may perceaue, if he be not tooto [sic] partiall, and ouermuch carryed away with affection, that such an assembly cannot be the true Church of God.</title>
            <author>Wright, William, 1563-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26046.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143286</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143286</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1884:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle dedicated to an honourable person in the which are discouered a dozen bad spirits, who from the beginning haue much haunted &amp; grieuously tormented the Protestant congregation, so that euery one may perceaue, if he be not tooto [sic] partiall, and ouermuch carryed away with affection, that such an assembly cannot be the true Church of God.</title>
                  <author>Wright, William, 1563-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.c   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[St. Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Imprinted, M. DC. XXII [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and publisher from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Attacks an "Epistle written by N.E."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, torn, tightly bound, and with print show- through, and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴, E².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Epistle written by N.E.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28358:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE DEDICATED TO AN HONOVRABLE PERSON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the which, are diſcouered a dozen bad ſpirits, who from the beginning haue much haunted, &amp; grieuouſly tormented the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Congregation: ſo that euery one may perceaue, if he be not tooto partiall, and ouermuch carryed away with affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſuch an Aſſembly cannot be the true Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted, M. DC. XXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:28358:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> thing els can enſue, but that in lieu of true faith they reap nothing els but ſome humane opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſome other phantaſticall illuſion, which is as farre from diuine fayth, as truth from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood, and a blacke Diuell from an Angell of light.</p>
            <p>But becauſe no Sect can be ſupported with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome certaine meanes, in place of all thoſe infallible grounds, which are in vſe amongſt Catholikes, and euer haue beene ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles tyme, they haue brought in the ſpirit of <hi>Rayling,</hi> of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>Lying,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction,</hi> and euery ones <hi>Priuate</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>For D. Luther ſayth: That there be as many ſects and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among vs, as there be men, Ther is no Aſſe in this time ſo ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſh and blockiſh, but will haue the dreames o his ownef head, and his opinion accepted for the inſtinct of the holy Ghoſt, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe eſteemed as a Prophet. Luther ep. ad An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>werp. tom. 2 Germ. lenae. fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>01. The Centuriſts tearme all the followers of the Confeſſion of Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, Ecebolios, and likes them to the fiſh</hi> Poul-countrell, <hi>which changeth often his colour, and to the old Pagan God</hi> Vertumnus, <hi>who coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelfe into all ſhapes, and tell vs: That they now approue the true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trine, and preſently after condemne the ſame, now calling that hereſy, which before they preached as an vnconquered truth. Cent. 9. in pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and fancy;</hi> and by the vſe of theſe they bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and vphould in ſome faſhion this their new vpſtart Congregation: which to be ſo, you ſhal eaſily perceaue in this my ſhort Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>And to begin. Among all thoſe monſters and bad ſpirits, with the which they haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred the world, the ſpirit of <hi>Contradiction</hi> is moſt familiar among them, ſeeing they do ſo excell in it, as none indeed, if he but looke into their writings, can tell whome to truſt or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue. For if you will but run ouer theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:28358:2"/> which this Parſon brings forth, in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, to moue your Honour to ioyne to his <hi>diſtracted</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">To Syr Edwyn Sands, they (to wit the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) are like ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red troups ech draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aduerſe way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any meanes to pacify their quarrells. In his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation f. 8. To learned Duditius, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines do coyne a monthly fayth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za ep. theo. 1. To Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, They know not whome to follow. Proteſt. Apol. pag. 509. To learned Maior, The ſimple doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any true Church of God be yet remayning. In orat. de conſuſ dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. N. E. epiſt. pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Congregation,</hi> you ſhal ſee nothing affirmed by him, which ſome of his famous brethren will not deny, and nothing denyed by him as falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which another of his owne coate more learned then he, will not affirme to be moſt true. Thus then hath our iuſt God ſtroken them with the ſpirit of giddynes and diſagreement, as while they endeauour to build vp their hereticall Tower of Babell, their own labours fall vpon them, and cruſh them down to their vtter ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But to the end, your Honour may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand we do them no wrong, we will make a ſhort ſuruey, and caſt the eyes of our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, ouer ſome pointes of this Miniſters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arring Epiſtle, in which, this Parſon firſt tells you, <hi>That Giant-like Catholiks fight againſt Chriſt and the primitiue Church,</hi> about Communion in one kind, as though it were vnlawfull to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer one kind to the people, or that Chriſt had giuen ſome Commandement, as concerning that point: wheras D. Luther <note n="c" place="margin">D. Luther. They ſinne not againſt Chriſt, who vſe one kind, ſeeing Chriſt hath not commanded to vſe it, but hath left it to the will of euery one, ſaying: As often as you do theſe, you ſhall do them in memory of me. De captiuit. Bahyl. cap. de Euch.</note> the Patriarch of all the Reformers, will tell you a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary tale to that of this petty Miniſters, to wit,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:28358:3"/> that neither the giuing of the Communion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one kind by the Prieſt to the people, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, nor that there was euer any command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, enacted by Chriſt, for receauing it <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> that is vnder both kinds.</p>
            <p>Againe he tells You, that Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion now is a new inuention, and was no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">N. E. ep. pag. 8.</note> of fayth before the Councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> which was 1215. yeares after Chriſt. But <hi>M. Fox</hi> his Reuerend Father, will teach your <note place="margin">Fox Act. mon. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1576. p. 1121.</note> Honour, how this Parſon lyes lewdly, becauſe according to him, <hi>aboue 100. yeares before this tyme denyall of Tranſubstantiation began to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Hereſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer he tells you, that the adoring of the Sacrament, or Chriſt contayned in it, is <note place="margin">N. E. ep. pag. 8. Kemnit. in exam. Conc. Tri. par. 2. pag. 91.</note> 
               <hi>Idolatry.</hi> But <hi>Kemnitius</hi> one of the famous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants that euer were, will informe you of the contrary, That none doubteth to adore it, but he who with the Sacramentaryes denyeth Chriſts body to be preſent.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe this Parſon would haue you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that it is not Chriſts body which is really <note place="margin">N. E. ep. pag. 3.</note> in the B. Sacrament, but a naile to faſten true Chriſtians to the Croſſe of Chriſt. But what euer Scripture tould this Parſon it was a naile? Chriſt ſayth <hi>This is my body,</hi> expreſly, <hi>which is to be giuen for you,</hi> and this Parſon ſaith, it is not <note place="margin">Matth. 26.</note> Chriſts body, but a <hi>nayle.</hi> Whom will you rather beleiue, Chriſt who is truth it ſelfe, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceaue, or this miniſter who is a lyar, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:28358:3"/> we haue ſeene, and commonly doth nothing but deceiue.</p>
            <p>Againe, he would delude you with this <note place="margin">N. E. in his epiſt. p. 3.</note> his interrogation ſaying, <hi>Who doth deny the reall preſence?</hi> as though none denyed it; which is ſuch a groſſe vntruth, as I thinke the Deuill himſelf is not wont to ſuggeſt a groſſer. For doth not <hi>Luther</hi> long ſince conclude againſt <note place="margin">Beza epiſt. Theol. 1. pag. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> from whom <hi>Caluin,</hi> as <hi>Beza</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, doth not diſſent, <hi>that the Deuill by Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius and his adherents, laboureth to ſup vp the egg,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luth. ſer. de Euc han. fol. 335.</note> 
               <hi>and leaue vs the ſhell,</hi> that is, as he expoundeth himſelfe, <hi>to take from the bread and wine the body and bloud of Christ, ſo that nothing remaine but plaine Bakers bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neyther would this Parſon haue you beleiue, that Chriſt can put his body in more <note place="margin">N. E. ep. pag. 9.</note> places togeather at once. For the which his <hi>Reuerend</hi> Father D. <hi>Luther,</hi> &amp; all the <note n="*" place="margin">M. Fox ſayth: Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byding in heauen is no let, but that he may be in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if he liſt. Act mon. pag. 998. Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſayth: The Controuerſy in this matter is not what may be, but what is. Chriſt body may be as well in the bread, as in the dore and ſtone. In his anſwere to Gardiner pag. 454. See M. Reynolds anſwere to M. Bruce his ſermons p. 349. N. E. ep. pag 9.</note> prime Proteſtants, will knock him ouer the thumbes, and tell him, that it is blaſphemy to deny this to the omnipotent power of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>He would haue you beleiue, that you ought to <hi>yeild this reſpect to the Scriptures, as to profeſſe, that they are a full and ſufficient rule for precepts of Holines, and neceſſary matters of faith.</hi> But his learned brother M. <hi>Hooker,</hi> will tell you another tale. <hi>Of thinges neceſsary</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:28358:4"/> 
               <hi>very chiefest is to know what bookes, we are bound to esteem holy, which point is confeſſed impoſsibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">M. Hook. in his Eccl. po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icy. l. 1. ſect. 14.</note> 
               <hi>the Scripture it ſelf to teach: for if any booke of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture did giue teſtimony to all the rest, yet ſtill that Scripture, which giueth testimony to the reſt, would require another Scripture to giue credit vnto it; neyther could we euer come to any pauſe whereon to reſt, vnleſſe beſids Scripture ther were ſome thing which might aſſure vs.</hi> And thus you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this Parſon reiecting <hi>Traditions,</hi> doth not beleiue the Scripture according to M. <hi>Hooker:</hi> which notwithſtanding, this Parſon tells vs, is <note place="margin">N. E. ep. pag. 12.</note> the ground of his faith, which not beleeuing as he ought, for any thing that we know, he may <note place="margin">Kemnit. exam. par. 3. p. 200. D. Fulke ſayth: I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that Ambroſe, Auguſtin, and Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, held Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints to be lawfull. In his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder to Briſtow pag. 5. Epiſt. pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 13. Symonds on the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations pag. 57.</note> be a Iew, a Turke, or an Infidell, and ſo no fit man to bring your Honour to his faithleſſe Congregation.</p>
            <p>He would haue you beleiue, that one <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gnapheus, a pernicious Heretique, was the first that ſhuffled in, the Inuocation of Saints into the praiers of the Easterne Churches.</hi> But <hi>Kemnitius,</hi> a greater Clearke then this Parſon is, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince him of this groſſely, and tell him that the <hi>Inuocation of Saints, was brought into the publique aſſemblies of the Church by</hi> Baſil, Nyſſen, <hi>and</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen, <hi>about the yeare</hi> 370. which was aboue a hundred yeares before <hi>Gnapheus</hi> was borne.</p>
            <p>This Parſon would haue your Honour beleiue, that Images are not to be worſhipped, as though it were a new Inuention. But his brother M. <hi>Symonds,</hi> will tell him, that it is not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28358:4"/> ſo new as he would haue you beleiue: for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to him, <hi>S Leo decreed, that Reuerence</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Damaſ. l. 4. cap. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould be giuen to Images,</hi> which was about a 1200. yeares ſince: and <hi>Damaſcene</hi> will tell <note place="margin">Niceph. l. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hiſt. c. 27.</note> you, that <hi>it is a Tradition of the Apoſtles:</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> That <hi>the audacious ſpirit and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent mouth of</hi> Xenaias, <hi>was the first that euer vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mited out this ſaying, That the Images of Chriſt &amp; of thoſe whom Chriſt loueth, are not to be reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced:</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Perkins ſayth, how</hi> Paulinus <hi>writeth, That the B. of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eaſter yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſet forth the Croſſe for the people to worſhip himſelfe being the chief of the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. In his problem p. 81. In the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his epiſtle. Luth. tones 5. VVite. in pſal. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 166. in Galat. c. 50 fol. 416. Sebaſt. Franc. Chron. part. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. f. 263, Theol, Heidelberg in Protocol. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. in prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. ad Antha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Theol. Manſfeld, in confeſſ Manſfeld. lac. fo 120 M Bernard of VVorſop against the Separatiſts. See dangerous poſitions for the Puritans againſt the Proteſtants. And M. Barow. and M. Smith againſt Bernard of VVorſop, &amp; al both Puritans &amp; Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi>
               </note> others.</p>
            <p>All his Epiſtles runnes in this veine of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arring and warring againſt his learned bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, greater Doctours then himſelfe, ſtuffed vp with no fewer blacke lyes and vgly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, then irreconciliable iarres and moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt contradictions, of the which I haue ſet downe twenty about the B. Sacrament onely; and no fewer might be laid open about the reſt if it were thought expedient. But to ſhew how this contradicting ſpirit, doth dominere in this Parſon, I thought them ſufficient; which is alſo inough to diſcouer, the vgly ſpirit of ſchiſme and hereſy, againſt whom God is not wont to fight by force or ſubtilty, but with the ſpirit of giddines and diſagreement: for ſo ſaith D. <hi>Luther; that the authors of ſchiſme are diſagreeing among themſelues; they bite and deuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re one another, till at laſt they periſh. This the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:28358:5"/> of all times do testify. After that Affrick was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Staniſlaus Reſcius in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entur. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarum. Fitzberb. of Policy and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on part. 2. pag. 449.</note> 
               <hi>ouerthrowen by the Manichees, then preſently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Donaſtes, who diſagreeing among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues were deuided into three ſects &amp;c. In our time the Sacramentaries first, and then after the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts deuided themſelues from vs; nether of them are at vnity among themſelues: ſo allwaies ſect bringeth forth ſect, and one condemneth another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the very ſame argument, is yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made manifeſt againſt the Anabaptiſts, by <hi>Sebastian Francus,</hi> &amp; the Deuines of <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> and alſo againſt the Sacramentaries by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> by the Puritans againſt the Proteſtants in England, and the Proteſtants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Puritans, and the <hi>Brownistes</hi> againſt them both: ſo that <hi>Staniſlaus Reſcius,</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth among them 170. diſtinct ſects, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers far more: and this euery one may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter belieue, if he conſider that it is very hard, to find any two of the learned ſort of them of one opinion, teaching all principall matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>Hence it commeth to paſſe, that they are not afraid to cenſure and condemne one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of hereſy. For if we belieue <note n="*" place="margin">VVe ſeriouſly iudge the Zuinglia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes to be heretikes &amp; aliens from the Church of God, So Luth. theſ. 81. contra Lou. Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 7. in defenſ. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae fol. 38, be ſayth: Touching the ſoule, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we will auoyd them as long as we liue, we will reproue and condemn them for Idolaters, corrupters of Gods word, blaſphemers and deceauers; and of them as of enemyes of the Ghoſpell, we will ſuſtaine perſecution &amp; ſpoile of our goods, whatſoeuer they ſhall do vnto vs. The Zuinglians of <hi>Zuricke</hi> complaine that Luther inueigheth againſt them, as againſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Heretikes, and ſuch as are guilty to themſelues of all impiety, &amp; the moſt vile &amp; peſtilent men that go on the ground. Confeſſ. orthodoxa. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Tigur. in praefat. fol. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Luther,</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:28358:5"/> the Lutherans, <hi>Zuinglius, Caluin</hi> and the other Sacramentaryes are damned Heretikes; and if we giue credit to <hi>Zuinglius, Caluin,</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, both <hi>Luther</hi> &amp; the Lutherans are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſame crime. And no leſſe will D. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell</hi> auerre of the Proteſtants and Puritans in <note place="margin">D. Couell in iuſta &amp; temperata defenſ. pag. 07. art. 11.</note> England. <hi>For least any thinke that our contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>are of ſmall matters, and that our difference is not great, we haue both condemned one another of hereſy, if not Infidelity; and of thoſe pointes which quite ouerthrow the groundes of our Christian fayth.</hi> And the fountain from whence all theſe ſo bitter iarres and warres do proceed, is the want of ſome certaine and infallible rule to direct them; for ſeeing all ſeeme to accept of the bare word of Scriptur, for the only grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of their faith, interpreted according to their owne priuate ſpirit, and fooliſh imagination, which whether it be true or no, he cannot certainely tell, ſeeing that ſuch a ſentence, may admit diuers expoſitions; and yet becauſe he thinketh, that he can defend that new inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation inuented by him, although not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet at leaſt with ſome colour, or ſhew of truth, he preſently by defending it obſtinatly, is made the author of a new Sect.</p>
            <p>Hence M <hi>Parkes</hi> ſpeaking of our Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <note place="margin">M. Parkes Apolog. ſupra epiſt. dedicat.</note> writers, ſayth: <hi>Euery man maketh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hand-mayd of his affections: we may ſay now that there are as many fayths as wills, and ſo many doctrines as manners of men, whiles either we write
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:28358:6"/> them as we list, or vnderſtand them as we pleaſe; in ſo much that many are brought to their wits end, not knowing what to do. Men ſay they know whom to flye, but whome to follow they cannot tell. This age is the last and worst, wherein hereſy and infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ioyne and labour, to ſubuert and ouerthrow all groundes of Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this bad ſpirit of Giddines and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, aryſeth another no leſſe ſcandalous among the Reformers, called the <hi>Spirit of Rayling,</hi> in the which they haue ſuch a talent as they ſpare none, whether he be Prince or Prelate, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, Puritan or Proteſtant, or whoſoeuer op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues, againſt their new found ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imaginations. With this ſpirit, Biſhop <hi>Barlow</hi> taketh vp <hi>Father Parſons</hi> (otherwiſe a religious <note place="margin">See D. Barlow his anſwere to the booke intituled, The iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of a Catholike Engliſhma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the we woath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. pag. 67. 63.</note> man and a worthy Deuine) telling vs, <hi>That he was a blacke-mouthed Shemey, famous for nothing but for capitall infamyes, a baſtard by birth, a libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler by cuſtome, a factioniſt in Society, an expulst Academian, rung out with bells as a carted ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet with pannes, for a graceleſſe companion, a Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Machiauellian, a ſtaine of humanity, a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupter of all honesty.</hi> Againe, <hi>A Camelion for his Profeſsion, a back-ſlyding Apoſtata, a periured in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder, a diſſolute libertine in act, in choice, in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, a fugitiue with diſcontented renagates, a viperous complotter againſt his Countrey, a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand of treaſonable combustions by pen and aduice, and which of all other is moſt remarkable, a Ieſuite by proxy, a Votary by ſubstitution, a Paduan Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanke,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:28358:6"/> and Empericall Qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaluer, a diſdainefull ſcorner of all reproofe or counſaile, and yet a ſcorned Vaſſal by all the Popes he had ſerued, a dog to ſnarle &amp;c. This cancker of youth, this ſpawne of vipers, this ſlaue of Satan &amp;c. A dead dog, being while he liues a rotten carcaſſe, of a poyſoned Cur, infected in his intralls, and infecting with his ſauour the ayre he breaths in, and the land wherin he had his first breath, a miching Cur, a carrionly Cur &amp;c. as if he were the porter of Hades, Carons maſtiue, Plutoes Cerberus, he harrowes Tartar, and (I tremble to write it) feignes with a wiſh, Queene Elizabeths glorifyed ſoule in gastly Ghost, to ſpeake from Hell.</hi> So farre Biſhop <hi>Barlow</hi> Prelat-like.</p>
            <p>Hence D. <hi>Luther</hi> againſt King <hi>Henry</hi> the <note place="margin">Luth. in lib cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Regem Anglia.</note> eight, rayleth thus, calling him: <hi>An enuious madd-foole, babling with much ſpittle in his mouth, more furious then madnes it ſelfe, more dotiſh then folly it ſelfe, endued with an impudent and whoriſh face, without any one veine of Princely bloud in his body, a lying Sophiſt, a damnable rotten worme, a Baſiliske and progeny of an Adder, a lying ſcurrill couered with the title of a King, a clowniſh wit, a dotiſh head, most wicked, foolish and impudent Henry.</hi> And ſayth further: <hi>He doth not only lye like a moſt vaine ſcurrill, but paſſeth a most wicked knaue; thou lyest in thy throate fooliſh &amp; ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King.</hi> Hence <hi>Eraſmus</hi> (a Confeſſour with <note place="margin">Eraſmus contra non ſobriam Lutheri <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtolam.</note> 
               <hi>Fox,</hi> and of good iudgment, &amp; a wel meaning man with <hi>D. Reynolds)</hi> telleth vs, that <hi>Luthers</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>breatheth deadly hatred, is all full of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:28358:7"/> if not furious reproaches and malicious lyes. He malepartly rayleth againſt Kinges and Princes when he liſts; extreme hatred, deſire of commaund and firebrands of inciters driue him out of the way, he craketh naught but Diuells, Satans, Hobgoblins, Witches, Megeraes, and ſuch more then Tragicall ſpeaches. His mind can be ſatiated with no rayling, he is beſides himſelfe with hatred, he hath no ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, no Chriſtian modeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither are the Puritans ſo honny-mouthed, as they would make men belieue; for now &amp; then out of their aboundance of this ſpirit, they beſtow ſome few ſprinklings vpon them who for their titles otherwiſe ought to be ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their Reuerend Fathers, and the chiefeſt Worthyes of the Proteſtant Church. Thus then, as though they had dipped their pen in gall, they ſalute the Engliſh Biſhops, telling vs: <hi>They are right puiſſant, poyſoned, perſecuting</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 2. of dangerous poſitions cap. 11.</note> 
               <hi>and terrible Prieſts, Cleargy Ministers of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focation houſe, the holy league of ſubſcription; the crew of monſters and vngodly wretches, that mingle heauen and earth togeather, horned Maiſters of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. VVhit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guift in reſp. ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſion: m<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>apud Fitg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim. in his Britan. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>the Conſpiration houſe, an Antichriſtian ſwiniſh rabble, enemyes of the Ghoſpell, moſt couetous wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and popiſh Prieſts, the Conuocation houſe of Diuels, Beelzebub of Canterbury the chiefe of the Diuels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if they rage thus againſt their Reuerend Fathers, what mildnes can we expect towardes their dearly beloued brethren? Verily, <hi>the</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:28358:7"/> 
               <hi>taunts and contumelies of ministers againſt mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> (ſayth M. Ormerod) <hi>are vnchriſtian, they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">M. Orme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rod picture of a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan fol. 3.</note> 
               <hi>refuſe to ſalute one another, wiſhing the plague of God to light vpon them, ſaying, they are damned.</hi> And thus with whole Cart-loades of dirtifying words, curſes, execrations and condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they beſmeare and bedaube their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, as els where I haue ſhewed; which is a moſt manifeſt ſigne, that the furious, raging &amp; rayling Spirit, doth much predominate among them.</p>
            <p>But beſides their Spirit of <hi>Contradiction,</hi> their Spirit of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> &amp; their Spirit of <hi>Rayling,</hi> there oftentimes ruſheth out another, no leſſe deforme and vggly then the former, which is the blacke Spirit of <hi>Belying their Aduerſaryes,</hi> for ſeing their Hereſies cannot be maintained with the ſpirit of Verity and Truth, they are enforced to vſe the benefit of that Spirit, which <note place="margin">O ſlander in Epitom. Cent. 16. pag. 796. See Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard of VVorſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p in his book of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts Schiſm. p. Campanus in Colloq. latin. Luth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſom. 2. c. de Aduer. fol 354.</note> is the enemy of that moſt noble Vertue, to wit the foule Spirit of <hi>Lying, falſhood</hi> and <hi>Vntruth;</hi> and indeed they ſo ioy and exult in this blacke art of lying, as the <hi>Lutherans</hi> report, how the <hi>Caluinists hould for a receiued principle and rule, that it is lawfull to lye for the glory of Christ:</hi> and thoſe of the purer ſort in England, tell vs, that <hi>the Protestants preach lies in the name of the Lord.</hi> And Campanus lets vs vnderſtand, <hi>that as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as God is God, ſo certaine it is that Luther was a Diueliſh lyar.</hi> And that this Epiſtler hath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably well learned this leſſon of lying, you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:28358:8"/> may perceiue partly out of that which hitherto we haue ſaid, &amp; partly out of this that he would <note place="margin">N. E. ep. pag. 3.</note> haue you beleiue, that in the article of <hi>Merits,</hi> the Proteſtants <hi>ſubſcribe to the Orthodoxal iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of S. Augustin,</hi> which is ſo falſe, as no leſſe man then D. <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf calleth in ſcorne, <hi>Hierome, Ambroſe, &amp; Auguſtin, Merit mongers of the ould Papacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe he would haue you beleiue that I cite D <hi>Iames</hi> to giue witnes againſt <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. pag. 5.</note> that he was in ſome point an Anabaptiſt, &amp; a Stoick: which is indeed a falſe lye, ſeing I do not ſo much as name D. <hi>Iames</hi> in the whole booke againſt Wickliffe.</p>
            <p>This Parſon would haue you beleiue, that the <hi>Testimony of Proteſtants for the Papacy,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſeparatly conſidered, is a worme-eaten pillar, too weake for the ſupportance of that Religion.</hi> But Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <note place="margin">D. Morto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſt. dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. in his anſwere to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy. D. VVhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale. contr. 292. c. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Morton</hi> will tell this Parſon he lyes, and informe your Honour, <hi>That the teſtimony of the Aduerſary is the greateſt reaſon of ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And <hi>D. Whitaker, That it must needes be a ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is taken out of the confeſſion of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He would haue you beleiue, that <hi>Watſon his teſtimony is true,</hi> affirming that the <hi>Ieſuits do confeſſe, that the ancient Fathers neuer touched</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pist. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>the thing of Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which for ought this Parſon knoweth is a moſt groſſe vntruth, ſeing <hi>Watſon</hi> publiquely at his death, craued pardon of the Ieſuits for the wrong he had done
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:28358:8"/> them; and that he wronged them in this, is ſo manifeſt, as euery one may ſee in <hi>Zuarcz</hi> &amp; <hi>Bellarmine</hi> onely, aboue 40. Fathers for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and beleife of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe he would haue you beleiue, that <note place="margin">Epiſt. pag. 11.</note> the Inuocation of Saints is not the ould way, but ſome new innouation: whereas D. <hi>Morton</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Morton Apol. par. 1. p. 217. 218.</note> will informe your Honour, how the quite contrary is moſt true, affirming, that <hi>all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity taught Inuocation of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Parſon would haue you beleiue, that Preiſts radically do not beleiue <hi>Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> becauſe ſome being required after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">Epiſt. pag. 8.</note> refuſed to ſay, <hi>God graunt I may haue no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by the bloud of Christ, if it be not in the Chalice;</hi> for, this they might moſt lawfully refuſe to do vpon ſome other ground, although moſt fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely and conſtantly they all beleiued <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Parſon perchance would haue you beleiue, that Catholike Prieſts are like his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, who are wont to teach one thing and beleiue another. No, no, this belongs to our new Rabbins, as they confeſſe themſelues. For M. <hi>Iohn Muſa</hi> this Parſons brother-miniſter <note place="margin">Ioannes Matthefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de vita Luth. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio. 12. fol. 147.</note> ſaith: <hi>Matheſius told me, that one time he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned very grieuouſly to Luther, that thoſe things which he preached to others, he himſelf could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiue:</hi> the which Luther hearing, anſweared. <hi>Now bleſsed be God, that the ſame happeneth to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that is wont to happen to me: For hitherto I</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:28358:9"/> 
               <hi>thought that none had done this but my ſelf.</hi> Was not this a Rogiſh tricke, in theſe prime pillars and chiefe Reformers? How can any giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credit, if they iuggle thus, in matters concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning either our cheifeſt good and ſaluation, or our eternall ruine and deſtruction?</p>
            <p>Beſides all theſe wicked ſpirits, our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers haue foure or fiue more, with whom they are very familiar, to wit, the ſpirit of <hi>Pride,</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>Liberty,</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>Carnality,</hi> the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and laſtly the <hi>Diuell</hi> himſelfe, who is as it were the Lord and Prince of all theſe. But to ſpeake a word of euery one.</p>
            <p>Out of the ſpirit of <hi>Pride,</hi> they ſwagger like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and condemne, and contemne all Fathers, all Councells, and Churches. <hi>For what haue we to doe with Fathers, with fleſh and bloud</hi> (ſayth D. Humfrey) <hi>or what is it to vs, what</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey in prafat. ad Orig. Beza in his preface v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the Prince of Conde. ann. 1587. Luth. lib. contra Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>480.</note> 
               <hi>the falſe Synods of Biſhops do decree? Seeing</hi> (ſayth Beza) <hi>that Sathan was preſident in their aſſemblyes and Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elis.</hi> But to be briefe, out of D. <hi>Luther,</hi> who was the firſt Father, you may take a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling how to iudge of the reſt. <hi>Henry</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>for his Maſſing ſacrifice bringeth in the ſayings of Fathers; heere ſay I, that by this meanes my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is confirmed: for this it is which I ſayd, That the Thomiſticall Aſſes haue nothing which they can alleadge, but a multitude of men, and the ancient vſe. But I, againſt the ſayings of men Fathers, Angells, and Diuells, put downe the Ghoſpell, which is the word of the eternall Maiesty; heere I inſult</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:28358:9"/> 
               <hi>ouer the ſayings of men though neuer ſo holy; ſo that I care not though a thouſand Augustines and Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians ſhould ſtand against me.</hi> And in another place hauing reiected Fathers, Councells, ſchooles and ages, he thus concludeth: <hi>Neither</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luth. de ſeruo arbit apud Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. in defenſ. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog.</note> 
               <hi>let the multitude, magnitude, latitude, profoundi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, miracles, ſanctity of the Church of Saintes moue thee a iote; all of them were damned if they thought as they write.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of the ſame Proud Spirit, although by their owne confeſſion, they are couered ouer <note place="margin">Caluin. in antid. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Trid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſ. 6. cap. 5. 10. 13. 15. &amp; lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Inſtit. c. z. Pareus in Prologom. ad Oſcam Proſ. D. Luth. tom. 1. in 1. Petr. c. n.</note> from top to toe, with filth, vncleanes, &amp; meere iniquity; yet neuer theleſſe they boaſt and brag that they are all holy and ſanctifyed from their mothers wombe, all certaine of predeſtinatiô, iuſtification and ſaluation, <hi>All equall in honour and dignity to</hi> S. <hi>Paul, S. Peter, the Mother of God, and all the Saints in heauen; that they all haue receaued the ſame treaſure from God, and all that good is, as largely as they, that they are all Saints; and that he is accurſed, who doth not call himſelfe a Saint.</hi> In the meane tyme they thruſt Chriſt Ieſus out of his eternall throne, telling <note place="margin">Cart wrig. 2. Repl. p. 191. Caluin. in cap. 3. ad Galat. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. inſtit. cap. 7. §. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Beza in c. 17. Matt.</note> vs, <hi>That he was ſeene to be a miſerable man, truely a ſinner, doubtfull of his ſaluation, deſerued nothing of God, but burst out into a voyce of deſpaire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus they triumph in their <hi>Lucifer</hi>-like pride, as I ſayd, againſt Chriſt and his Saintes, although the Scripture, which they would make the world belieue is their entire rule of fayth, hath no ſuch blaſphemous ſpeaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:28358:10"/> Chriſt, but the quite contrary, to wit, <hi>That he was the ſplendour of his Father, the figure of his ſubſtance, without ſpot, or blot of ſinne, the fountaine of all grace and vertue, to whome was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a Name aboue all Names, power both in heauen and earth, to raiſe himſelfe from death to life, to aſcend into heauen, to ſit at the right hand of his Father, and to cruſh all his enemyes vnder his feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not deny but <hi>Spangeberge,</hi> is ſomwhat <note place="margin">Cyriacus Spangeb. contra Stepha. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricol. fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. a.</note> more modeſt then others, ſeeing that although he preferre <hi>Luther</hi> before all the Saints of God, the Apoſtles, yea and our B. Lady that thrice renowned Queene of Heauen, yet he puts one before him, to wit <hi>S. Paul,</hi> ſaying:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christus habet primas, habeas tu Paule ſecundas:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At loca post Paulum proxima Luther habet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt place to Chriſt, the next to Paul,</p>
            <p>Then Luther firſt of others all.</p>
            <p>Heere hence it is no wonder, that <hi>Conradus Riſse</hi> tells vs in plaine tearmes: <hi>That God did take from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itzherb. 2. part of policy and Religion. pag. 453. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 31.</note> 
               <hi>him</hi> (to wit Luther) <hi>the true ſpirit for his pryde, and gaue him inſteed thereof, an angry, proud, and lying ſpirit &amp;c.</hi> Thus far of their ſpirit of pride.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit of <hi>Liberty</hi> is the <hi>broad way that leadeth to perdition,</hi> which indeed they haue made ſo broad, as I do not ſee, how the Diuell can well deſire a borader. For firſt they reiect the ten Commaundements as impoſſible; the <note place="margin">Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 2. inſtit. c. 7. §. 5.</note> Lawes of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> or the Ceremoniall law, is abrogated, and Chriſt our Sauiour made none; and humane lawes do not bind in conſcience,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:28358:10"/> and therefore they infer, how they are freed from all. <hi>Hence</hi> (ſaith Caluin) <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caluin. l. 3. inſtit. c. 19. §. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>conſisteth in three parts; firſt that the conſciences of the faithfull, while they with the confidence of their Iuſtification, do raiſe themſelues aboue the law, do forget the whole iustice thereof. And after. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, that mention of the law being taken away, they onely imbrace Gods mercy.</hi> And §. 4. <hi>Our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are free from the yoake of the law.</hi> And §. 7. <hi>he reiecteth all humane lawes,</hi> as well Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical as ciuill, which are made about thinges of their owne nature indifferent. <hi>The third part is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that we make no ſcruple of externall thinges, which are of themſelues indifferent, but that we indifferently vſe or omit them.</hi> Hence he inferreth that no man is obliged to humaine lawes, concerning faſting and holy daies.</p>
            <p>This liberty of the Ghoſpell is founded in two principles, the one is, that the Pope is <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for by this is taken away the Canon Law; the other, that we are not bound to obey <hi>Kinges</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> if they commaund any thing not conteyned in Scripture, and thereby are both Imperiall, and Municipall, which we call the common Lawes, aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>Thus far of the Libertine ſpirit of <hi>Iohn Caluin</hi> which he may be thought to haue ſucked from D. <hi>Luther,</hi> and his moſt learned ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. <note place="margin">Luth. de libertate Chriſtiana. Idem ad c. 2. ad Galat</note> For thus diſcourſeth <hi>D. Martin. Onely Faith, &amp; the Word doth raigne in the ſoule; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is manifeſt that only faith ſufficeth a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:28358:11"/> 
               <hi>man for all thinges, and that he needeth no workes for his Iuſtification: and if he needeth no workes, he needeth no Law; if he need no law, he is free from the law; and it is true, that the law is not made for the iuſt.</hi> Thus argueth <hi>Luther:</hi> &amp; vpon the ſame ground he affirmeth reſolutely els where. <hi>Onely Faith is neceſſary that we may be iust, al other things are most free, nether commanded any more, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luth in c. 7. ep. 1. ad Cor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And againe in another place. <hi>Thou art bound to God in nothing, but to beleiue and confeſſe him, in all other thinges he maketh thee free, that thou maieſt do according to thine own will, without any offence of conſcience.</hi> This being the doctrine of <hi>Luther</hi> the Maiſter, it is not to be wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred at, if ſome of his ſchollers, haue drawen out theſe, &amp; the like poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, all tending to the enlarging of <hi>the liberty</hi> of this fifth new inuented Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. <hi>The law</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is not worthy to be called</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Confeſſio Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld in ſecta Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomorum,</note> 
               <hi>the VVord of God: if thou be a whoore, or a forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catour, or an Adulterer, or any other ſinner what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, onely beleiue and thou art in the way of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, euen when thou stickest fast in the very mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of thy ſinne. The ten Commandments belong to the Court, but not to the Pulpit. Whoſoeuer haue any thing to do with Moyſes, do go the right way to the Diuell &amp;c. The ſaying of Peter,</hi> Make ſure your vocation by good workes, <hi>is vnprofitable. Whenſoeuer thou haſt any cogitation, that any meanes is to be vſed, that men may be good, honeſt, and holy, &amp; chaſt, thou art already gone aſtray from the Ghoſpell.</hi> Heereupon ſayth D. Luther:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:28358:11"/> 
               <hi>Let vs take heed of ſinnes, but eſpecially of good workes.</hi> And others tell vs, <hi>How we ought to pray to God, that we may remaine conſtant euen vnto the end, without all good workes, ſeeing that good workes are not neceſſary, but hurtfull and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to our ſaluation; And that Chriſtians with good workes belong to the Diuell.</hi> To the which they adding that the beſt worke they do, can be no better then a mortall ſinne; we inferre, that they are bound, in conſcience neuer to do any good worke.</p>
            <p>And becauſe their fayth, according to <note place="margin">D. VVhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tak. Fides aut eſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petua aut nulla. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Camp. rat. 8. pag 143. Luth. in 2. part. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillae prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Arge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Germ. an. 1537. fol. 140. Luth. tom. 1. ep. lat. n. folio 334. ad 1 hilip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum.</note> D. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> once had, can neuer be loſt, they may giue full ſcope, and looſe their raines largely to all liberty and looſenes of life. <hi>For as nothing doth iuſtify but fayth, ſo nothing</hi> (ſayth Luther) <hi>doth damne, but infidelity.</hi> And althogh the Apoſtle tell vs; <hi>That Fornicators Adulterers and ſuch like, ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heauen;</hi> Yet out of D. Martin, <hi>Sinne cannot withdraw vs from Chriſt, although we ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit fornication and murder a thouſand times a day.</hi> But truely if we may be as great Saints in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as the Apoſtles, our B. Lady the thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Mother of God, or any other Saint in heauen how great ſoeuer, and yet haue liberty to kill and murther a thouſand tymes a day, contemne all lawes both of God, and man, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faſt, or do any worke of pennance; who will ſay, that this way to heauen is ſtraite, and not rather ſo broad, as all the blacke ſpirits in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:28358:12"/> hell, for the increaſe of ſinne, and amplifying of the Diuels Kingdome, can ſcarce inuent a broader.</p>
            <p>But if we add that of M. <hi>Wotton,</hi> who tels vs, <hi>That ſinne is remitted as ſoone as committed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">VVotton in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the popiſh art. p. 41.</note> 
               <hi>the faythfull perſon hauing receaued the remiſſion of all his ſinnes past, preſent, and future togeather;</hi> we ſhall ſee ſuch a floud gate opened to all kind of vice &amp; villany, that I thinke the very great Diuell of hell would haue beene aſhamed by himſelfe, to haue publiſhed either in print or in pulpit ſuch a Libertine Poſition, if it had not beene vnder the maske and vizard of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter called M. <hi>Wotton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the ſpirit of <hi>Carnality,</hi> I am very loth to ſpeake any thing for feare of offending your chaſt &amp; modeſt ears; but ſeing our Proteſtants are ſo familiar with this foule ſpirit, the matter is of great importance, to ſee them ſo drowned in this filth as they are, which is ſo oppoſit to the pure ſpirit of God, as one contrary can be to another. Therfore I would deſire your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience although you heare ſomewhat contrary your owne Noble Diſpoſtion, ſeing it cannot but redound to the great confuſion of all our moderne Nouelliſts, and to the great good of others.</p>
            <p>And to begin. They allow and proue <note place="margin">Luth. tom 9. de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rimonio fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>18.</note> that <hi>Fornication, Adultery,</hi> and <hi>Poligamy</hi> is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Fornication is taught by <hi>D. Luther,</hi> in calling <hi>the maid, if the wife</hi> be ſtubborne, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:28358:12"/> ſhould <hi>refuſe.</hi> Adultery, according to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> who married <hi>Heſter</hi> and put away <hi>Vaſthy;</hi> who likewiſe ſaith, that <hi>if the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band be impotent, the wife may either marry another or with his conſente ſecretly lye with his brother, or ſome other man.</hi> And indeed theſe new Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers haue beene ſo frantick and mad with this ſpirit, as to thinke it no leſſe impoſſible for a man to liue chaſt then to fly ouer the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane <hi>Caucaſus.</hi> For thus ſpeakes <hi>D. Luther: As</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luth. in colloq. Germ. cap: de Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio.</note> 
               <hi>no man can liue (ſaith he) without meate or dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk. ſo no man can abstaine from a woman &amp;c. and the cauſe is, that we are conceiued in a woman, and nouriſhed there, and borne of a woman, fedde, and bred of a woman, and thereupon it followeth that we cannot by any meanes be ſeparated from women.</hi> And in the ſame book he goeth forward thus; <note place="margin">Zuinglius tom. 1. fol. 115. Ochin. dial. l. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ial. 21. p. 200. 204. Luth. de Bigam. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſ. prop. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. Idem in Geneſ 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Martyr in 1. Cor: 7.</note> 
               <hi>S Hierome writeth many thinges of the tentations of the fleſh; Ah, a ſmall matter, A woman, in a mans houſe may remedy the diſeaſe; Euſtochium might eaſily haue helped or releiued Hierome in that caſe.</hi> Thus ſaith he. And could any ſhameleſſe Ribauld, ſpeake more ſhamefully of Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants &amp; holy Saintes? Zuinglius &amp; his fellow miniſters of the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelicall doctrine confeſſe, that they did burne with luſtfull deſires of the fleſh, <hi>&amp; by meanes thereof were made inſamous be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the Congregations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ochinus, Luther, Peter Martyr,</hi> and others playing the part of Iewes and Turkes, allow
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:28358:13"/> plurality of wiues. <hi>Beza</hi> was infamous for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring <note place="margin">Beza in ſua Creof. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. Bolſec. in vita Calu.</note> 
               <hi>Andebertus</hi> his boy, before <hi>Candida</hi> his ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet, &amp; <hi>Caluin</hi> for his Sodomy at <hi>Noyon</hi> was branded on the ſhoulder with a hoat burning iron. And this carnall Miniſter is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to tell your Honour, that when I ſtile <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> doctrine <hi>licentious</hi> and <hi>beastly,</hi> for allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing in ſome caſe, <hi>Fornication,</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi> I make <hi>of a Mole hill, a Mountaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to be breife, <hi>the ministers themſelues are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zecanori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us lib. de corruptis moribus.</note> 
               <hi>not contented with one wife,</hi> as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth <hi>Syluester Zacanorius</hi> ſaying: <hi>O good God, what incredible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hinges haue I ſeene &amp;c.</hi> And among many other enormities of Adulteries and Murthers, he ſaith: <hi>One of them</hi> (he had killed his wife with poyſon to vſe other women) <hi>being demaunded why he had committed ſo great a crime; he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that marriage in Lutheran miniſters doth not extinguiſh wandring luſts;</hi> although they giue ſuch ſcope of diuorce in this matter of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, as Libertine <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, that a man may haue ten or more wiues fled from him, and yet all liuing.</p>
            <p>But now go tell theſe carnall &amp; fleſhly <note place="margin">D. VVhite in his way to the true Church. p. 395. Tyndall alleadged by Fox Act. mon. pag. 1337<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Libertines,</hi> that Fornication, Adultery, Inceſt, Poligamy are moſt grieuous ſinnes, and that all ſuch ſhall be accurſed and caſt downe into the eternall flames of hell fire prepared for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and his Angells; preſently they will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere out of <hi>M. Tindall</hi> (who was, as <hi>D. White</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:28358:13"/> writes, <hi>a man ſent from God to call his people out of Babylon) that Chriſt hath ordained that there ſhould be no ſinne but Infidelity, no Iuſtice but Fayth.</hi> And ſo according to the doctrine (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) of this man of God, Fornication, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Inceſt, Poligamy, Sodomy, Murder, and ſuch like, are no ſinnes at all, and therfore not to be feared. Out of <hi>Beza, That Dauid by his murder and adultery, did not looſe the Holy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Beza in Reſponſ. ad Act. col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisbelg. part. altera pag. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Luth tom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. VVitt. ſerm. de 4 Matrimon. fol. 119.</note> 
               <hi>Ghoſt.</hi> And out of D. Luther, <hi>That ſinne cannot withdraw them from Chriſt, although they ſhould commit fornication and murder a thouſand tymes a day.</hi> And indeed the ſatisfying of theſe beaſtly luſts, in the prime Pillars and chiefe Proteſtant Reformers, may be thought to haue beene one of the principall ends, at which they aymed, when they ran firſt out of their Cloiſters, and Monaſteryes, caſt off their religious habits, turned renagates from God, Apoſtataes from their ſacred and holy Orders, and of vowed Prieſts became ſacrilegious marryed Miniſters, from whome ſprouted out this Parſons new trimmed vp Congregation, of the which ſo much he braggeth.</p>
            <p>Of their ſpirit of <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> I haue ſpoken elswhere, as of their tending to Atheiſme; and therefore, now only I would haue your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to marke, that theſe two ſpirits, are not peculiar to ſome of the meaneſt among them, but to ſuch as are eſteemed great Rabbins and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:28358:14"/> Apoſtles of this Congregation, eſpecially if they be compared with this petty Miniſter, <hi>Parſon Eſtwicke</hi> For learned <hi>Eckhard</hi> tels vs, that <note place="margin">Eckhard. in faſciculo Contro. c. 7. queſt. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Caluin, Beza. Martyr, Boquinus, Renicherus, &amp; others are become ſo impudent, as they are not afraid to write, that God is the firſt, the chiefe, the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and decreeing, yea the prouoking, creating, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and enforcing cauſe of ſins.</hi> Out of which doctrine ſome Reformers proue, that all theſe Proteſtants turne <hi>God into the Diuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer <hi>D. Luther</hi> not without blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy would haue vs belieue, that chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Luth. in confeſſ. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ori de coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Domini &amp; lib. de Concuiis part. 2.</note> and dyed vpon the Croſſe, according to his Diuinity. <hi>For if I belieue</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that only the humane nature of Chriſt ſuffered for me, Chriſt is a baſe Sauiour, not of any great price, or valew, yea he himſelfe needeth a Sauiour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence Zuinglius exclaimeth, <hi>This can by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zuingl. tom. 2. in reſponſ. ad Luth. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ f. 458 469. 470. &amp; in reſp. ad Luth. l. de ſacra. f. 411. 401. 337. Ibidem. p 401.</note> 
               <hi>no reaſon be explained or excuſed: for</hi> Luther <hi>clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and manifestly confeſſeth, that he will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Chriſt to be his Sauiour, if only his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity had ſuffered.</hi> He calleth him alſo <hi>Marcion,</hi> and ſayth, <hi>he is guilty of moſt high blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the nature and eſſence of God.</hi> And elſwher, againſt <hi>Luther</hi> he writeth thus: <hi>If thou contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meliouſly go on in this ſentence, that the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chriſt Ieſus, is eſſentially and corporeally preſent whereſoeuer is his diuinity, God willing we will bring thee to theſe straites, that either thou ſhalt be forced to deny the whole Scripture of the</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:28358:14"/> 
               <hi>new Teſtament, or to acknowledg</hi> Marcions <hi>hereſy. This I ſay in good fayth, we promiſe we will do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>D. Bilſon</hi> tells vs, <hi>That the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. Bilſon in his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey p. 467. Idem in praefat. p. 466. 474. &amp; defenſ. pag. 126. 122. Bilſon pag. 490 defen. pag. 134. Bilſ. pag. 496. 486. defenſ. pag. 131. 136. Bill. pag. 497. 503. defenſ. pag. 197. 138. Bilſ. p. 55. defenſ. pag. 141. Bilſ. pag 517. defenſ. pag. 142. Parks ep. dedicat. &amp; pag. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. &amp; ſect. 20.</note> 
               <hi>cleare not Chriſt from ſinne. It was rife in the pulpits and vſuall in the Catechiſms</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that the death of Christ Ieſus on the Croſſe, and his bloud ſhed for the remiſsion of our ſinnes, were the least cauſe and meanes of our Redemption.</hi> And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting further theſe Proteſtants doctrines thus he relateth them, <hi>Christs wil was contrary to Gods will; Christ in his agony knew not Gods will; Chriſt was forſaken both in body and ſoule; Chriſt ſuffered hell torments; Chriſt ſuffered the paines of hell; Christ ſuffered the death of the ſoule; the death of the ſoule is ſuch paines and ſufferings of Gods wrath, as alwayes accompany them that are ſeparated from the grace and loue of God; God did forſake Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee, how our moſt B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, Redeemer of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind, &amp; conſequently as well all Chriſtians, as all others, are damned with him by theſe blaſphemous Proteſtants. Laſtly <hi>M. Parkes</hi> tels vs, <hi>That the perſon of Chriſt is prophanly ſpoken of; the Scripture is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifyed to fasten blaſphemy vpon Chriſt, heauen &amp; hell, the Diuinity and Humanity, yea the very ſoule and ſaluation of Christ our Sauiour himſelfe is called in queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to conclude, although it be an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Creed, <hi>That Chriſt ſhall come to iudge the quike and the dead, and that he will render to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:28358:15"/> one according to his workes;</hi> yet <hi>D. Luther</hi> moſt blaſphemouſly vomiteth out this helliſh <note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. tom 1 Germ. VVittem. fol. 273. §. 3.</note> ſpeach: <hi>When Chriſt comes to thy mind as a Iudg, which is to command thee to giue vp the reckonings of thy stewardſhip, or of thy life now at an end, be thou aſſured</hi> (ſayth Luther) <hi>that he is not Chriſt, but the Diuell himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſhew that they are tormented with the ſpirit of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> will be witneſſe worthy <note place="margin">Zanchius in his epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle before his confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pag. 7. D. King. vpon lonas §. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. pag. 442. D. VVhit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guift. in his defence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ract. 3. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 278.</note> 
               <hi>Zanchius,</hi> who affirmeth, <hi>That among other mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Atheiſme hath beene fetcht out of hell, by the Ministers of Sathan, in ſome of the reformed Churches.</hi> And Doctour King late Biſhop of London, ſayth: <hi>So farre is it off, that we are become true Iſraelits with Nathanael or but almost Chriſtians with Agrippa, that we are proued fully Atheists.</hi> To whom we may add <hi>D. Whitguife</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who tells vs in plaine tearmes, <hi>That the Church of England is repleniſhed with Atheiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that they want not the Diuell to teach &amp; inſtruct them, &amp; to be as it were a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar friend with them, to make them aquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Hoſp. in biſt. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. part. altera fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. Courad. Riſſ. lib. Germ. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Ioan. Heſſi. de C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with all theſe former ſpirits, they will not deny themſelues. For <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> ſayth, <hi>That Luther being taught by the Diuell, that the Maſſe was wicked, and being ouercome with Sathans arguments, did therupon abandone the Maſſe.</hi> And another Proteſtant tels vs, <hi>That Luther bought a familiar Diuell of</hi> Caroloſtade <hi>for four ſhillings.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:28358:15"/> And <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe bluſheth not to ſpeake thus: <hi>The Diuell ſleepeth neerer and oftener by me,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luth. in Collo. men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> f. 271. 275.</note> 
               <hi>then my Katherine; and Satan fauoureth me much more then he doth others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He alſo tells vs, <hi>That the cauſe why the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentaryes do not vnderſtand the Scripture, is,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luth. in colloq. de vero Deo pag 33. Luth in colloq. Pranck. f. 18. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hluſſel. in prafat lib. de Theol. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uinist.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they want the true opponent, to wit the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, who at length is wont to teach them very well: for when we haue not ſuch a Diuell hanging about our neckes</hi> (ſayth Luther) <hi>we are nothing but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatiue Deuines.</hi> But <hi>Conradus</hi> tels vs, that for all this the Caluiniſts or Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taryes do not want the Diuell for their maiſter and ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: <hi>For it is certaine</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaryes do deſtroy and ouerthrow the Testament of the ſonne of God, with dreames ſuggeſted vnto them by the blacke Diuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, <hi>D Luther</hi> ſayth: <hi>That we are held captiue by the Diuell, as by our Prince and God, ſo that we are forced to do what ſoeuer he will, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luth. tom. 3. Germ. Ien f. 247. Luth. in colloq. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal. de oper: Dei p. 49. Vide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio. Luth. de Domin. loeta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inter 27. concio. VVittem. &amp; Arge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. impreſſ. 46 fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>ſuggeſteth vnto vs.</hi> Heere you ſee how <hi>Luther</hi> makes no bones, to challeng the Diuell for his God. And in another place: <hi>I know not whether I teach truth or no</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>for very often Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than doth aſſault me, and oppreſſe me ſo violently, as altogeather I forget Christ. I haue the Diueill within me, and I know him in his skin, becauſe he hath eaten more then a buſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſalt with me: he is wont to walke with me in the Dormitory; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially I haue two pleaſant Diuels who are Doctors of</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:28358:16"/> 
               <hi>Diuinity in this Colledge, and obſeruers of all my actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer he was ſo deuout to the Diuell, <note place="margin">In colloq. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nenſal. Germ. fol. 281. 285.</note> as he was wont to pray to him in this manner, ſaying: <hi>O holy Sathan, pray for vs, for we haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer offended thee, O most clement Diuel.</hi> Conradus alſo tells vs, <hi>That the ſpirit of the Caluinists is the ſpirit of darcknes, and that Sathan doth ſpeake by the Caluiniſts, as by his owne inſtruments.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <note place="margin">Conrad. l. 3. Ther. Calu. art. 8. Conrad. ibid. in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aem. Oſiand. in Euchir. cont. Calu. pag. 267.</note> 
               <hi>That it is more cleare then the Sunne ſhining at midday, that not the true God but the Diuell himſelfe, did ſuggest to</hi> Zuinglius <hi>the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary hereſy in a dreame.</hi> And Oſiander likewiſe ſayth, <hi>Let any godly or friendly Reader think what deadly poiſon Sathan doth power out into men, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Caluinian doctrine, by which almost all Chriſtianity is ouerthrowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And another famous Proteſtant called <hi>Iezlerus,</hi> would haue vs know, <hi>That the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans call the Zuinglians conuinced Heretikes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iezler. lib. de diutur. belli Euch. p. 93.</note> 
               <hi>of euery ſide poſſeſſed, aboue, before, behind, within and without with Diuels; to be numbred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Anabaptists, Neſtorians, Arrians, Turkes; to be the wickedeſt men that liue vpon the earth; &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be damned for all eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude, another Proteſtant cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Ioannes Schutz</hi> hath publiſhed in print; that <note place="margin">Schutz. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. cauſ. in praefat.</note> the ſect of the Sacramentaryes <hi>is a certaine ſink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into which many hereſyes flow; the last wrath o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sathan the which he stirring vp in his rage, dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:28358:16"/> exerciſe against Chriſt and his Church.</hi> Of this ſect <hi>M. Zuinglius</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> were prime pillars whoſe deaths were anſwerable to their liues. For of <hi>Vldricke Zuinglius</hi> his ſtate and death, to whome <hi>the Diuel ſuggested the Sacramentary he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy,</hi> D. Luther hauing condemned him <hi>for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Heretike, accounts him bleſsed that ſtands not in his way, and exhorteth euery one to flye his bookes, no otherwiſe then the poyſon of the Diuell of hell. He is a man</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>ſo vnto ward, that he hath loſt Chriſt wholy: and I confeſſe</hi> (ſayth D. Martin) <note place="margin">Tom. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 80 de Aduero,</note> 
               <hi>ingenuouſly, that I cannot place him now amongst Christians; he teacheth no article of fayth truly, &amp; is ſeauen tymes worſe then when he defended the Popes fayth and Religion. God is a iuſt Iudge, &amp; his iudgments are right, who ſuffereth not the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temners of his word to go vnpuniſhed, but to periſh miſerably. And laſtly, to the end he might bring others to his errour, he went to warre, and there was ſlaine and dyed like a thiefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Franciſcus Stancarus</hi> his cenſure of <hi>Caluin</hi> is this. <hi>Beware</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Stane. lib. 4. contra Caluin. N6 4.</note> 
               <hi>and chiefly all you Ministers: I ſay, beware of Caluins bookes, and eſpecially of the articles of the Trinity, Incarnation, and Mediatour, of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme, and Predeſtination; for they containe impious doctrins, Arian blaſphemyes, that it ſeemeth the ſpirit of</hi> Seruetus <hi>who was burnt, (according to the Platoniſts opinion) hath paſſed into Iohn Caluin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:28358:17"/>
            <p>And <hi>Scluſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urge</hi> a Superintendent, and one of the moſt famous men, that euer were among the Lutherans, ſayth: <hi>God that woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not be mocked by men, hath ſhewed his iudgment i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Schluſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. art. 9. Theol. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. f. 72.</note> 
               <hi>this world againſt Caluin, viſiting him by the ſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of his fury, and horribly puniſhing him before the day of his death: for he stroke this Sacramentary Heretike in ſuch ſort, as he dyed deſperate ſwearing and calling vpon the Diuell, to whom he gaue vp hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wicked Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, if this Proteſtant Aſſembly by the Proteſtants owne confeſſion, be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation ſtuffed with the ſpirit of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> of <hi>Lying,</hi> and <hi>Rayling,</hi> againſt all kind of people, friends and foes, Peeres, Prelates, and Princes; a Congregation ſwelling with Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer-like <hi>Pride</hi> in the higheſt degree, teaching the baſeſt miſcreant in it to perfer himſelf in matters of faith, before all Doctours, all Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all generall Councells and all Churches, and in ſanctity of life; although they be truely nothing elſe, but a meere maſſe and puddle of iniquity (as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſayth) to equall themſelues to the greateſt Saintes that euer were, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the mother of God; a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation taught doubtleſſe by the ſuggeſtion of Sathan, to contemne all lawes of whatſoeuer ſort, both humane and diuine; a Congregation infected with the ſpirit of all kind of liberty, lechery, and lewdnes of life, and yet aſſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:28358:17"/> the followers of it, to be as ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of their Predeſtination, Iuſtification &amp; Saluation, as Chriſt himſelf; a Congregation loaden with horrible Blaſphemies, and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hfull ſpeaches, againſt Chriſt our Sauiour, and the liuing God; repleniſhed with Atheiſts, and fraught with Deuills, &amp; ſo many kinds of vncleane ſpirits: If, I ſay, this Proteſtant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation be ſuch an Aſſembly, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues do acknowledge and confeſſe; I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that this Parſon was not aſhamed to be ſo ſenſeles, and without braynes, as to inuite your Honour to be a member thereof.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
